Animation Number 1
Large Photomultiplier Tube
Humans have a desire for truth.
（貝木(かいき)）
人は真実を知りたがる
Or they have a desire to believe that what they know is the truth.
あるいは
Nobel Prize in Physics Laureates
1818                                1975                                1988                               1999
自分の知っているものを
真実だと思いたがる
In other words, the actual truth comes second to that desire.
つまり 真実が何かなどは
二の次なのだ
Be mindful of what is truth and what is a lie.
何が真実で何がウソなのか
気をつけながら
In other words, always doubt yourself. Harbor an inner devil's advocate as you read along...
つまりは 常に疑いながら
心に鬼を飼いながら読むことを
お勧めする
And I won't forget to add that by that point, you might have already fallen into my trap.
もっとも その時点で俺のわなに
はまっているのかもしれないと
付け加えておくことを
忘れる俺でもないが
Now then, here's a tale where lies and truth intertwine,
では では
虚実入り交じる描写
あることないこと織り交ぜて
weaving in things that did and didn't happen.
戦場ヶ原(せんじょうがはら)ひたぎと阿良々木(あららぎ) 暦(こよみ)の
恋物語を語らせてもらおう
I'm going to tell the love story of Senjougahara Hitagi and Araragi Koyomi.
Improved
Luck
Kaguya
Improved Luck
Good Luck
I'll guarantee its quality, if not its truth.
真実かどうかは保証しないが
クオリティーは保証する
I hope from the bottom of my heart that there's an ending where every reader will say...
最後に読者全員が“ざまあみろ”と
思えるような結末が
あの２人に訪れればいいと
心の底から俺は思う
..."Serves them right!"
That is, if I even have a heart. That is, if I even exist.
俺に心があればだが
俺なんてヤツがいればだが
Then, in a comical way, let's start the final story!
それでは面白おかしく
最後の物語を始めよう
Just kidding. Of course, this may be a lie too.
なんて もちろん
これもウソかもしれないぜ
End of Second Term
Animation Number 19
Hitagi End          Part One
Font used in the video: HGP Mincho B
Animation Number 20
1st of January
That day, I was at some famous shrine in Kyoto, Japan.
（貝木）
その日 俺は日本京都府京都市の
とある有名な神社に来ていた
It's New Year's Day.
元旦である
I was at a shrine on New Year's Eve to ring in the new year, so to say.
神社に来ているのは
元旦ゆえの二年参り
というわけだ
And that's a lie. It was partially for fun, to observe visitors...
というのはウソである
遊び半分で神社を訪れ
...throwing away money, more important than their lives, as if it were nothing but trash.
命よりも大事な金を
ごみか何かのように
放り投げる人間を観察するために
I came to a shrine to study the ecology of people of that nature.
そういう人間の生態を
研究するために
Upstanding, ordinary citizen.
Animation Number 39
俺は
神社にやって来たのだ
Ordinary citizen afraid of doubt.
Animation Number 41
That story sounds pretty legit, but the actual reason may be completely different.
というような話をすれば
それっぽいかもしれないが
実際は全然 別の理由かもしれない
The Ones You Wait For   Will Come
Things You Lost   You Will Find Elsewhere
Your Travels   Will Be Great
Your Business   Will Bustle After Some Improvement
In reality, maybe I went to wish for a healthy year or to find a good match for me.
本当は 今年１年の健康を
...is not a good idea.
...should stay inside
...end in disaster
...be abandonded.
...is not a good idea.
...should stay inside
...end in disaster
...be abandonded.
Improved
Luck
あるいは 良縁でも
祈りにいったのかもしれない
Concerning me, the pursuit of "maybes" may be an endless task. Maybe.
とか 俺に関して
“かもしれない”を追及すれば
切りがない かもしれない
Unknown Name
Hello, Kaiki? It's me, Senjougahara Hitagi.
（戦場ヶ原）
もしもし 貝木？
私よ 戦場ヶ原ひたぎ
A name like a deadly blade.
Animation Number 56
Tamikura-sou
There is someone I'd like you to deceive.
あなたに
だましてほしい人間がいるの
Animation Number 60
Don't play dumb. This is Kaiki, right?
（戦場ヶ原）
とぼけないで　貝木でしょう？
My name is Suzuki.
（貝木）私は鈴木(すずき)といいます
Suzu, as in a bell on a collar, and ki like giving a blunt answer.
首輪に付ける“鈴”に
木で鼻をくくるの“木”
と書いて鈴木です
Excuse me, who'd you call? And Senjougahara? I have no recollection of such a name.
失礼ですが
どちらにおかけですか？
戦場ヶ原？
まるきり覚えのない名前ですが
I see. Then Suzuki's fine. Rather than Senjougahara, we can say I'm Senshougahara.
（戦場ヶ原）
そう じゃあ鈴木でもいいわ
Senshougahara Hitagi
私も戦場ヶ原じゃなく
千沼ヶ原(せんしょうがはら)でいいわ
Senshougahara. Who's that?
（貝木）
千沼ヶ原？
Senshougahara.
Animation Number 70
誰だ？
Senshougahara.
Animation Number 70
Senshougahara
Mikadoyama
No, where?
いや どこだ？
I was careless,
Animation Number 72
and started listening to her.
Suzuki, there's someone I'd like you to deceive.
Senshougahara Hitagi
o Group
（戦場ヶ原）
鈴木
あなたに
だましてほしい人間がいるのよ
I'd like to meet and talk, so where should I go? Where are you now anyway?
直接会って話したいんだけれど
どこに行けばいい？
そもそも
今 あなた どこにいるの？
Okinawa. In a cafe in Naha, Okinawa. I'm eating a morning set in the cafe.
（貝木）
沖縄　沖縄の那覇市の喫茶店だ
喫茶店でモーニングを食べている
Got it. I'll head there now. My shoes are already on.
（戦場ヶ原）
分かった 沖縄ね　今すぐ行くわ
既にもう靴を履いたわ
I'll call when I'm at the airport. You'd better keep your phone on.
そっちの空港に着いたら電話する
携帯の電源は
ちゃんと入れておきなさいよ
If my call doesn't go through, I'll kill you.
つながらなかったら…
ぶっ殺すから
I'm leaving this in your hands.
よろしくお願いするわ
Unknown Name
（貝木）
よろしくお願いする
She's leaving this in my hands.
My.
Animation Number 82
Regards.
Animation Number 83
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
In any case...
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
とにかく
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Sun Airways
202-201 13-16
On that day, due to the silly lie I made, I had no choice but to head down to Okinawa.
俺は その日 自分のついた
くだらないウソのために
Tokyo
Okinawa
沖縄に行かなくては
ならなくなってしまったのだった
Animation Number 87
Would she, a girl whose identity I don't know, have someone that she wants to deceive?
（貝木）
あいつに… 誰だか分からないが
あの娘に だましたいと思うような
人間がいるのか
Would someone who suffered as a victim of fraud think of fooling someone the same way?
詐欺の被害に遭い
ひどい目に遭った人間が
同じように
人をだまそうなどと思うものなのか
Interesting. I have to look at this with an inquisitive eye.
興味深い
好奇の目で見ざるをえない
Such a girl... I don't know who she is, but asking me of all people to be an accomplice in her fraud...
そんな彼女が
誰だか知らないが とにかく彼女が
ほかならぬ この俺に
詐欺の片棒を担げと言うのだから
...is the epitome of unnatural.
不自然極まりない
I've never fallen for a swindle,
Animation Number 96
but, you know,
based on what I've heard,
Animation Number 96
victims don't change into aggressors;
they usually stay victims forever,
Animation Number 96
in my opinion.
In that respect, I just feel something's wrong. If I had to rephrase...
その点においては違和感しかない
...it's not that I feel something's wrong. I just have a bad feeling.
あえて別の言葉を探せば
違和感ではなく
嫌な予感というやつだ
This errand bodes ill.
Animation Number 100
Animation Number 104
Unknown Name
Kaiki? I'm here.
（戦場ヶ原）
貝木？　着いたわよ
Who's that? I said my name was Suzuki, Senshougahara-san.
（貝木）
貝木とは誰でしょう？
私は鈴木といいます 千沼ヶ原さん
That's enough of the unnatural acting. Stop with the childish behavior already.
（戦場ヶ原）
わざとらしい演技は
もういいでしょう
Emergency Exit
いつまでも子供っぽいまねを
続けるのは やめてちょうだい
Where should I head?
（戦場ヶ原）
私は どこに行けばいいの？
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Senshougahara-san. Actually, I'm already near the airport in an effort to pick you up.
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（貝木）
千沼ヶ原さん
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（貝木）
実は既に空港のそばまで
千沼ヶ原さんを
迎えに上がっております
I see.
（戦場ヶ原）
あら そう
Since you took the time to come down as my client, I felt it natural.
（貝木）
クライアントに わざわざ
ご足労いただいたのですから
それが当然だと
Therefor, we should meet in the airport lobby.
ですから 空港のロビーで
お会いしましょう
Oh my, I'm grateful for your thoughtfulness.
（戦場ヶ原）
まあ まあ　ありがたい気遣いね
I totally thought you just flew in to Okinawa...
てっきり
あなたも日本のどこかから
沖縄に飛んできたところなのか
と思った
...from elsewhere in Japan, and just arrived at the airport like me.
私同様に
空港に着いたばかりなのかと
I have no clue as to what you are alluding.
（貝木）
何をおっしゃっているのか
全く意味が分かりませんね
I see. Well, whatever.
Buy a Ryuukyuu Beauty as your souvenir!
Ryuukyuu Beauty
Super Popular
Charm
（戦場ヶ原）
そう　まあ 何でもいいわ
Lobby is such an abstract location. Can I meet you in a cafe or something inside the airport?
ロビーというのでは あいまいね
空港内の喫茶店かどこかで
会えないかしら？
All right. We can do that.
（貝木）
分かりました
では そうしましょう
After I enter the cafe, should I call you to tell you the shop's name?
（戦場ヶ原）
店に入ってから店名を
電話で知らせればいいのかしら？
（貝木）
いえいえ
空港内の喫茶店 全てを巡って
I'll walk through every cafe in the airport to make sure I'm the one who greets you.
Okinawa Soba
Onion Beer
Okinawa
必ず こちらから
お声がけいたしますので
Okinawa Soba
So Senshougahara-san, please elegantly have some tea and wait a bit.
千沼ヶ原様は優雅に紅茶でも
飲みながら お待ちくだされば
After all, this is our first meeting.
（戦場ヶ原）
お互い 初めて会うのだし
I'll have some glasses on, so use that as your sign that it's me.
（戦場ヶ原）
眼鏡をかけているから
それを目印にしてちょうだい
Animation Number 130
Animation Number 134
I felt like I had lost.
Animation Number 143
Beaten in a competition.
（戦場ヶ原）ぷは！
（貝木）
ヘヘッ よし勝った
All right. I win.
Hot coffee, please. And one more glass of orange juice for this lady.
（貝木）ホットコーヒーを
それから こちらの女性に
オレンジジュースを もう１杯
It's been a while, Senshougahara.
久しぶりだな 千沼ヶ原
It's been a while, Suzuki.
久しぶりね 鈴木
Animation Number 165
To think that you'd be the one contacting me.
（貝木）
お前から俺に連絡してくるとはな
どうした？　何かあったのか
What's wrong? Something happen?
There is someone I'd like you to deceive.
だましてほしい人間がいるのよ
Would you be up for the deception?
だましてもらえるかしら？
I'm troubled that the request is very vague.
漠然と言われても困るな
Of course, there is no human that I cannot deceive...
もちろん 俺に
だませない人間などいないが
...but without a more concrete story, I can't give an answer.
しかし具体的な話を
聞かせてもらえないかぎり
返事はできない
Even if you're not respectable, I'm trying to save your face as you are older than me.
（戦場ヶ原）
一応 目上ではなくとも
年上ではある
あなたの顔を立てるつもりで
That is why I'm taking the format of a commission.
仕事の依頼という形を
取っているだけで
Fundamentally, you have to do something of this level to begin with.
あなたは本来 それくらいのことは
しなければならないのよ
What's up with that?
（貝木）
なんだ そりゃあ？
償いというやつか？
Are you talking about atonement?
Because I previously got you into a terrible situation, I have to make up for it?
昔 お前を
ひどい目に遭わせたのだから
その埋め合わせをしろとでも？
That's, you know...
そりゃあ 何というか…
大きくなったな 戦場ヶ原
...showing growth on your part, Senjougahara. On something other than your boobs...
おっぱい以外も
It's not to make up for something you've done against me.
私に対する埋め合わせでは ないわ
All the pain you caused me has already been made up by Araragi.
あなたに傷つけられた分は
阿良々木くんに
ちゃんと埋めてもらったもの
Oh, well that's splendid. Not a cheap shot.
（貝木）
ほう そりゃあ重畳(ちょうじょう)　お安くないな
So, you're making up for something completely different.
（戦場ヶ原）
だから あなたが埋め合わせるのは
全く別のものよ
And you must do it.
あなたは必ず
そうしなければならない
I'm slightly disgusted by having my actions limited like that.
（貝木）
そんなふうに
自分の行動を制約されるのは
いささか嫌気が差すな
I mean, I can turn away and go home right now.
なんなら今すぐ
俺は帰ってもいいんだ
If you do that, I'll stab you.
（戦場ヶ原）
そんなことをしたら刺すわよ
私が何の用意もなく
ここに来ていると思わないで
Don't think that I came here without making any preparations.
I don't want to be stabbed.
刺されるのは嫌だな
I have no choice. I'll at least listen to your story.
しかたがない
話くらいは聞いてやろう
Though I don't know if I'll do it after hearing the story out...
言うことを聞いてやるかどうかは
分からないが
Go ahead, tell me, Senjougahara. Who and where do you want me to deceive?
聞かせろよ 戦場ヶ原
お前 俺に どこの誰を
だましてほしいというんだ？
From how you've been talking, it sounds like someone I know.
なんとなく口ぶりからすると
俺の知っている人間っぽいが
Sengoku Nadeko.
千石撫子(せんごくなでこ)
Animation Number 192
Does Araragi know about this?
（貝木）
阿良々木は知っているのか？
That you're seeing me like this on New Year's day.
お前が こうして元旦から
俺に会っていることを
In the first place, aren't couples supposed to do the New Year's shrine visits together...
そもそも彼氏彼女というのは
元旦に 一緒に
初詣をするものではないのか
...and carelessly throw money away like trash?
お金を ごみのように
手荒く放り投げながら
Don't mock me. Of course he doesn't know.
バカにしないで
知らないわよ もちろん
If Araragi-kun were to see you, he'd be likely to kill you.
阿良々木くんが あなたに会ったら
あなたを殺しかねないものね
To that hero of justice, you are a natural enemy.
あの正義の味方にとって
あなたは天敵だもの
（貝木）ふん 知らない　つまり…
He doesn't know, so...
In other words, you came here to meet me in secret without Araragi knowing.
つまり 阿良々木に秘密で
俺に会いにきたというわけか
What of it?
それが何よ？
Is that something you repeatedly, or even once, need to confirm?
そうやって何度も いえ １度だって
わざわざ確認するようなこと？
No, not really.
（貝木）いや 別に
で なんだ？
So, what is it? To spend valuable time during your last winter break in high school with Araragi...
阿良々木との高校生活最後の
貴重な冬休みの時間を費やしてまで
In other words, you want to become an accomplice to a fraud so much...
つまり 彼氏に秘密を作ってまで
お前は詐欺の共犯者に
なろうというのか？
...that you created a secret you're keeping from your boyfriend.
I have no idea who this Sengoku Nadeko is. Is she a rival for his heart or something?
その千石撫子というのが
誰かは知らないが
恋敵か何かか？
In the first place, Araragi-kun is preparing for college entrance exams...
（戦場ヶ原）
そもそも
阿良々木くんは受験生だから
...so he's stuck studying, whether it's winter break or New Year's Day.
冬休みだろうと元旦だろうと
勉強漬けよ
（貝木）ふ〜ん
Well, I don't know how well Araragi does academically...
まあ 阿良々木の学力が
どの程度かは知らないが
...but if you're attending to his studies all the time, I'm sure he has no problems either.
お前が つきっきりで
教えてやっているというのならば
きっと問題ないのだろう
Both of you will be in college in the spring.
春からは
２人とも大学生というわけだ
No.
いえ
At this rate, Araragi-kun and I won't  have a spring or anything after.
このままだと 私と阿良々木くんに
春以降はないのよ
Hmm?
We have no future.
（戦場ヶ原）私たちに未来はないの
Hmm?
（貝木）あん？
Araragi-kun and I, if everything goes according to plan, are going to be murdered on graduation day.
（戦場ヶ原）私と阿良々木くんはね
順調にいけば 卒業式の日に
殺されることになっているの
ほう
I see...
So, something is going against you and Araragi for some reason...
つまり お前と阿良々木が
何かで恨みを買って
...and this Sengoku Nadeko wants to kill both of you,
その千石撫子とかいうヤツに
殺されそうになっているから
そいつを なんとか
言いくるめてほしいということか
so you want me to wheedle her into not doing so?
For the most part, you're correct.
おおむね正解よ
Still, murder is something far from peaceful.
（貝木）
しかし 殺されるとは
穏やかじゃないな
Right. It's not peaceful. It's very scary. Very ominous.
ええ　穏やかじゃあないわ
とても怖い 恐ろしい話よ
Can I tell you in a bit more detail, Kaiki-san?
詳しい話を
聞いていただけるかしら？
貝木さん
All you have to do is listen. If you say no, then I'll give up.
聞いてくれるだけでもいいの
あなたがダメだと言うのならば
諦めるわ
I'll give in and submit both me and Araragi-kun to die at her hands.
私と阿良々木くんは おとなしく
あの子に殺されることにする
If that is destiny that I can't avoid, then so be it.
それが避けられない運命ならば
しかたがないわ
No, if I were to plead with all my heart, maybe Araragi-kun will be spared.
いえ 私が精いっぱい
命乞いをすれば
阿良々木くんのほうは
助けてもらえるかもしれないわよね
I'll use that as my only hope to live the last two and a half months of my life.
それを唯一の希望にして
残り２か月半の余命を生きるわ
How gloomy.
Animation Number 227
However,
Animation Number 230
All right, I can just listen.
いいだろう　聞くだけならな
After getting it off your chest, you might feel better, and everything may work out.
話せば それで楽になって
すっきり解決してしまう
ということもあるだろうし
I answered thus.
Animation Number 234
Animation Number 235
I did say there was someone I'd like you to deceive.
（戦場ヶ原）
だましてほしい人間がいる
とは言ったけれど
But Sengoku Nadeko is no longer a human.
千石撫子は既に人間ではないわ
Oh? This is interesting. If she isn't human, what is she?
ほう 面白いな
人間でなければ 何だ？
A god.
（戦場ヶ原）神様
She became a deity of snakes. That was November of last year.
彼女は 蛇神(へびがみ)様になったの
それが去年の11月のこと
Let's just hear her out.
Animation Number 245
By becoming a god, do you mean...
神様になったというのは
...that she has an odd disease like the one you had? Is that how I should think of it?
お前と同じ奇病にかかった
Odd Disease
Animation Number 247
ということでいいのかな？
Yes, right.
（戦場ヶ原）ええ　そうね
Odd Disease
Animation Number 249
An odd disease, indeed.
Odd Disease
Animation Number 249
奇病ね
Odd Disease
Animation Number 249
It's true that we were both gods. I had a crab, and she has a snake.
確かに どちらも神様だし
私は蟹(かに)で あの子は蛇
Yes, an odd disease in a way.
そう まあ奇病よ
You did a job back in that town, so maybe you know...
あなた あの町で
仕事をしていたんだから
ひょっとしたら
知っているんじゃないかしら
...that there is a shrine named North Shirahebi Shrine atop the mountain.
山の上に北白蛇(きたしらへび)神社という名前の
神社があるんだけれど
That is where she is enshrined right now.
彼女は今
そこに 祭られているの
No, I don't know of any shrines by that name.
いや〜 そんな神社は知らんな
Is what I answered.
Animation Number 257
Of course I know it.
Animation Number 258
But I don't understand what you mean by saying she's enshrined there.
しかし
そこに 祭られているというのは
はっきり言って意味が分からないが
In other words, is Sengoku Nadeko a living deity that people show faith in?
つまり それは
千石撫子は現在 生き神として
信仰を受けているということか？
Living God
Animation Number 260
A living deity, in human form?
生き神とか 現人神(あらひとがみ)とか
Walking God
Animation Number 262
It's slightly different from things of that sort.
（戦場ヶ原）
そういうのとは
少し違うんだけれど
How to put it... She swallowed a god into her stomach.
神様を腹の中に
丸飲みしてしまったというか…
In any case, Sengoku Nadeko is no longer human...
まあ とにかく
千石撫子は もう人間じゃなくて
...and has turned into a monstrous abberation.
妖怪変化の類いということよ
I see.
（貝木）ふ〜ん
In other words...
（戦場ヶ原）要するにね
Sengoku Nadeko has become an incredible existence that common sense can't explain.
千石撫子は
とんでもなく ぶっ飛んだ存在に
なっちゃったということよ
An existence at a level that could crush that entire town if she wanted to.
その気になれば
あの町そのものを
つぶせるクラスの
そんな存在に
How did she come across such an odd disease in the first place?
（貝木）
その子は どうして
そんな奇病にかかったんだ？
From the sounds of it, I'm assuming that she's one of your classmates...
話を聞いていると
どうやら お前の同級生のようだが
Not so. Sengoku Nadeko is still in junior high.
（戦場ヶ原）
違うわ　千石撫子は中学生よ
What grade?
（貝木）中学何年生だ？
She's a second year.
（戦場ヶ原）２年生よ
Hey, Kaiki, are you asking on purpose?
ねえ 貝木
あなた わざと言っているの？
Hmm?
Does the name Sengoku Nadeko really not ring a bell?
（戦場ヶ原）
本当に心当たりがないのかしら？
千石撫子という名前に
ふん あの町
That town... That town you live in, and she's in junior high...
お前の住む あの町に住んでいる
中学生だということは
In other words, she's one of the junior high kids I deceived last year?
つまり 俺が去年だました
中学生の中の１人というわけだな
Strictly speaking, that's not true.
（戦場ヶ原）厳密には違うわ
Sengoku Nadeko was not a direct victim of your deception.
千石撫子は あなたの被害を
直接受けたわけじゃあない
She was a victim of one of your victims. I guess an indirect victim.
あなたの被害者から
被害を受けたのよ
間接的な被害という形に
なるのかしらね
（貝木）ほう
I see.
Tricked
Let's see... Fraud creates a chain reaction of victimization...
（貝木）
詐欺による
連鎖倒産のようなものか
Tricked
そうだな
...and that's why it's a menace to society that can't fit into the confines of the individual.
B
r
詐欺は
連鎖的に被害を生むから
o
k
e
Broke
個人の範囲に収まらない
社会悪なのだよな
Broke
Excuse me...
（ウエートレス）お客様
I'm sorry! She spilled her orange juice.
（貝木）すいません
この子がオレンジジュースを
こぼしてしまいました
I hate to inconvenience you, but can you get her one more glass, please?
申し訳ありませんが
同じ物を もう１杯お願いします
Don't treat me like a child.
（戦場ヶ原）子供扱いしないで
I'm sorry.
ごめんなさい
That's not the attitude of someone about to ask for a favor.
これから頼み事をしようとする
人間の態度ではなかったわ
Don't worry. Adults don't get upset at each mishap a child has.
案ずるな　大人は子供の粗相に
いちいち腹を立てたりはしない
In any case, even if indirectly...
（戦場ヶ原）
とにかく 間接的にとはいえ
...you were the one who dragged Sengoku Nadeko into the world of abberations.
千石撫子を怪異の世界に
引っ張り込んだのは あなたなのよ
If you can think that way, don't even man-eating fiends like you feel a bit of responsibility?
そう思えば あなたのような
悪鬼羅刹(あっきらせつ)でも
少しは責任を感じない？
I do, I do! The responsibility is crushing me to death.
感じる 感じる
責任感に押しつぶされて
死にそうだよ
I absolutely have to make up for it.
その償いだけは
絶対にしなくちゃな
I'll make up for it at any cost.
万難を排して償うよ
Tell me Senjougahara, what do you want me to do?
教えてくれ 戦場ヶ原
俺は何をすればいいんだ？
I'm telling you.
（戦場ヶ原）だから
Deceive Sengoku Nadeko, who is now a god, and save me and Araragi-kun.
神様となった千石撫子をだまして
私と阿良々木くんを
助けてほしいのよ
Help me.
Animation Number 292
I heard those words two years ago too.
（貝木）
その言葉を俺は２年前にも聞いた
I wonder how it feels to say the same line to the same person again.
同じセリフを
同じ相手に言うというのは
一体どんな気持ちなのだろう
I wonder how it feels.
どんな気持ちなのだろう
To save.
助ける
I save Senjougahara and Araragi.
俺が戦場ヶ原を
そして阿良々木を助ける
That all sounded like one bad joke.
なんだか その文言は
悪い冗談のようだった
And since I'm not one to dislike bad jokes, it put me in a pretty cheerful mood.
そして俺は
悪い冗談が嫌いではないので
結構愉快な気持ちになった
So you're telling me to deceive a god?
（貝木）
神様をだませというのか？　俺に
You can do that much, right?
（戦場ヶ原）
そのくらいできるでしょう？
You claimed that you're the best con artist on the planet,
曲がりなりにも あなたは
天下一の詐欺師を
うたっているのだから
so if you can't do it, what are you going to do?
むしろ それくらいできなくて
どうするのよ
I did not say that.
Animation Number 301
What? Do you have no confidence?
なによ 自信がないの？
I do.
あるね
Or rather, I don't need mere confidence to deceive a god.
というより たかが神様を
だますのに 自信なんかいらん
There is nothing that I can't deceive.
俺にだませない相手は いない
Then, you can deceive that girl filled with murderous intent...
（戦場ヶ原）
じゃあ 殺意にまみれた
その子をだまして言いくるめて
...and wheedle her into letting me and Araragi-kun live?
結果 私や阿良々木くんを
生き長らえさせることが
できるのね？
I can.
できるな
Strictly speaking, it's me, Araragi-kun, and the blonde girl that is Araragi-kun's loli-slave.
（戦場ヶ原）
厳密に言うと 私と阿良々木くんと
それから 阿良々木くんの
ロリ奴隷であるところの
金髪の女の子もなのだけれど
So easy. I'm perfectly fine even if there are five more loli-slaves.
余裕だ
ロリ奴隷が あと５人増えても
全然平気だ
I see. Then...
そう だったら…
But I'm only talking about how I can do it. Whether I'll do it or not is another matter.
ただし それは
できるというだけのことで
やるかどうかは別問題だ
In the first place, I deceive people for money.
そもそも 俺が人をだますのは
金のためだ
Why do I have to deceive Sengoku Nadeko when it doesn't bring in any money at all?
一文の得にもならないのに
どうして俺は その千石撫子を
だまさなければならないのだ？
Even if she's a god, to fool a girl in junior high makes my conscience hurt oh so much.
たとえ神様だとしても
中学生をだますなど 良心が痛んで
しかたがないじゃないか
Money... is something I'll pay, of course.
お金…
は払うわ　もちろん
I don't think you have enough of an income to say "of course."
（貝木）
ふん　もちろんと言えるほど
お前に支払能力があるとは
思えないが
I'll pay the money.
（戦場ヶ原）お金は払うわ
For starters, I can make a spot payment of 100,000 yen.
とりあえず
即金で10万円は用意できるわ
This is the price I paid Oshino-san when he helped me out.
これは忍野(おしの)さんに
お力添えいただいたときに
払った額よ
Back when Oshino-san fixed my odd disease...
忍野さんに
私の奇病を治してもらったときの
Then, you can take that money and ask Oshino again for this case.
（貝木）
だったら 今回も同じ額を払って
忍野に頼むんだな
I can't find Oshino-san. I've been looking for him.
見つからないのよ 忍野さん
捜しているんだけれど
Hanekawa-san even went overseas for me to look for him.
羽川(はねかわ)さんなんて
海外まで捜しに行ってくれたのに
Hanekawa?
（貝木）
羽川？
Hanekawa-san is one of my friends and classmates. She has big boobs.
羽川さんは私の友達で
クラスメート
おっぱいが大きい子よ
I already know the answer, but I'm betting on miraculous odds for now.
答えは分かっているけれど
一応 奇跡のような確率に賭けて
Kaiki, can I at least ask a question?
貝木 質問くらいは
させてくれるかしら
What is it?
何だ？
Do you not intend to work for free for me and Araragi-kun?
かつて迷惑をかけた
私や阿良々木くんのために
That is, to make up for what you did to Sengoku Nadeko and for the trouble you caused us?
それに 千石撫子に対する
埋め合わせのために
無償で働いてくれる
つもりは ない？
That would never happen even if heaven and earth flipped over.
（貝木）
それは天地がひっくり返っても
ありえない
Is 100,000 yen not enough?
（戦場ヶ原）10万円では足りない？
Well, it's not enough.
まあ… 足りないな
So just how much do I have to pay you to deceive Sengoku Nadeko for me?
だから 具体的には
いくら払えば
あなたは
千石撫子をだましてくれるのよ？
Demand an amount.
要求してよ
You can call the 100,000 yen your down payment.
10万円は とりあえず
手付けということにして
I'll prepare an amount that won't insult you.
失礼のない額を用意するつもりよ
You're really desperate when it concerns your life.
さすがに命が懸かると必死だな
それとも 恋人の命が大事
という感情なのかな
Or do you feel that your boyfriend's life is so important?
At the absolute limit that you could afford to pay...
もしも 払える限界の額で
阿良々木とお前
...if you could only spare one life, which would you pick? Your life or Araragi's?
どちらか１人だけの命が
助かるとなったら
お前は
どちらを選択するのだろうな
Araragi-kun. That's a given.
阿良々木くんよ
決まっているじゃない
Well, now...
まあ まあ
There are exactly 74 days until graduation.
卒業式までは
正確には あと74日ある
Given that much time, I can prepare a lump sum of money.
それだけあれば まとまったお金を
用意できなくはない
If I need to, I can sell my own body too.
なんなら 私の体を売っても
かまわないわ
Excuse me, where's the bathroom?
トイレは どこですか？
Now, time to ask myself.
さて自問自答だ
Do I feel like I want to work for Senjougahara and Araragi for free?
戦場ヶ原と阿良々木のために
無償で働いてやる気持ちは
あるか？
Do I feel like I can't bear to watch old rivals lose their lives in an unsightly manner?
かつてのライバルたちが
ぶざまに殺されるのを
見ていられないという気持ちは
俺には あるか？
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
That's a no. That would never be true.
ノーだ　絶対にない
If anything, I'd feel relief.
下手をすれば
俺は すっとしてしまうだろう
Then, would I be able to do anything for free for this girl named Sengoku Nadeko...
ならば 千石撫子という
奇病にかかってしまったらしい
娘のためなら
...who apparently contracted an odd illness?
俺は 無償で
何かができるだろうか？
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
That's a no. Who the hell is she?
ノーだ　誰だ？　そいつは
知らん
No clue.
Then, what if I base it on a desire to repay Senjougahara,
ならば かつてだました
純情な娘である戦場ヶ原に
an honest girl whom I previously deceived?
償いをしようという気持ちを
元にすれば どうだ？
Not as a rival, but as an old acquaintance.
ライバルではなく
旧知の間柄として
Do I feel like I want to do something for Senjougahara as a person, or for her family?
戦場ヶ原個人に対して
あるいは戦場ヶ原家に対して
何かしようという気持ちなら
俺には あるか？
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
That's a no. I don't feel like that at all.
ノーだ　そんな気持ちなんてない
I feel nothing toward that old case.
その件について
俺は何とも思っていない
Even if, as a result of my fraud, the daughter of the family decides to sell herself out,
（貝木）
たとえ俺の詐欺の結果
一家の娘が
身売りするはめになったところで
it wouldn't affect how I live one bit.
（貝木）
俺の生き方は
１ミリも動かないだろう
Then, what about Araragi?
だったら阿良々木は どうだ？
Right... I bullied his younger sister once.
そう あいつの妹を
いじめたことがあったな
I also sold information about him once to wrestle some money out of Kagenui.
それに影縫(かげぬい)から金をせしめるために
あいつの情報を売ったこともあった
As a small repayment for that, like giving change, how about I save his life?
その ささやかな お返しとして
つまりお釣りとして
ヤツの命を助けてやるというのは
どうだろう？
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
That's a no. Even if there was change for me to give back, it wouldn't be enough.
ノーだ
たとえ お釣りがあったとしても
いくら何でも 割に合わない
Such an amount was already used up just by coming here.
ここまでの交通費で
そんなものは消えている
Who else? Oh, right, that girl named Hanekawa?
あとは… そう そう
羽川という娘か
How about I be touched by a girl's admirable efforts to go overseas for the sake of a friend?
友人のために海外まで行くという
その度を超した娘のけなげさに
心を打たれてみるというのは
どうだろう？
Or perhaps she is amazingly rich.
あるいは その娘は とんでもない
お金持ちかもしれない
And maybe I can wrestle some money from her parents?
礼は そいつの両親からせしめる
というのは…
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
That's a no.
ノーだ
It did not require a moment's consideration,
Animation Number 364
nor to properly finish my sentence.
Hmph, no good. No matter how hard I think, I can't find a reason to accept this job.
（貝木）
ふむ ダメだ
いくら考えても この仕事を
受ける理由が見当たらない
Not only is there nothing in it for me, but I'd end up with a loss if I accepted.
何の得もないどころか
受けることが俺の損にしかならない
Oh, wait.
ああ そうだ
Come to think of it, that town is where she is...
（貝木）
そういえば
あの町には いたのだった
The niece of Gaen-senpai...
臥煙(がえん)先輩から見て めいにあたる…
In other words, the daughter...
つまり臥煙先輩の姉の
臥煙遠江(とおえ)の忘れ形見ともいうべき
...with which to remember Gaen-senpai's older sister, Gaen Toue, lives there.
一人娘がいたのだった
I believe her last name has changed and is now Kanbaru Suruga.
たしか 今は名字が変わって
神原駿河(かんばるするが)
Kanbaru Suruga is a student at Naoetsu High...
神原駿河は
直江津(なおえつ)高校の生徒で
しかも かつて戦場ヶ原とは
仲が良かったのでは なかったか？
...and wasn't she good friends with Senjougahara once too?
The first time I met Araragi was in front of Kanbaru's house.
俺が阿良々木と初めて遭遇したのは
その神原家の前だった
So if Araragi is connected to Kanbaru...
阿良々木が神原と
つながりがあるのだとすれば
...it's natural to think that Senjougahara has some sort of connection to Kanbaru as well.
当然のように戦場ヶ原と神原も
つながりがあると見るべきだし
And even if she doesn't, I'm at least certain that Kanbaru and Araragi are connected.
仮に なかったとしても
少なくとも神原と阿良々木が
つながっていることは確かだ
Whew.
Can I save my bitter enemies Senjougahara and Araragi, and deceive Sengoku Nadeko...
（貝木）
神原駿河のためなら
にっくき戦場ヶ原と阿良々木を助け
千石撫子をだますことが
俺には できるだろうか？
...for the sake of Kanbaru Suruga?
That's a yes.
イエスだ
Preview
Dialogue Script - Nisio Isin
4-Koma Illustrations - Haritama Hiroki
Preview
Karen here!
（火憐(かれん)）
火憐だぜ！
And Tsukihi!
I'm Tsukihi!
（月火(つきひ)）
月火だよ！
Together, we're the Fire Sisters!
We're the Fire Sisters!!
Love!
（２人）
２人合わせて
ファイヤーシスターズ！
Well, we're finally tackling the last previews of the long Monogatari Series!
Nadeko-chan is missing!
Let's look for her!
（火憐）
さあ長かった
物語シリーズも
いよいよ最終局面だぜ
Koimonogatari Hitagi End - will we make an appearance?
（月火）
「恋物語
ひたぎエンド」
私たちは
登場するのかな？
I hear we won't.
（火憐）
それは しないらしい
（月火）
それは しないんだ
Appear we won't then... Preview Quiz!
Have you seen Nadeko-chan?
Can't say I have...
Have I?
予告編ク〜イズ！
（火憐）
ク〜イズ！
Quiz!
Speaking of Tsukihi-chan, I'm dreaming of getting a pie haircut, however...
（月火）
月火ちゃんといえば
髪型を頻繁に
変えることで有名ですが
However?
（火憐）
有名ですが
You made us change hairstyles once, saying it was the age of ponytails.
（月火）
火憐ちゃんが
ポニーテールだった時代に
髪型を寄せていった
ことがあります
Have you seen
Nadeko-chan?
I only know what I know...
No luck...
（火憐）
ああ あった あった
Ah yes, I remember, the Ponytail Sisters.
ポニテシスターズに
なったんだ
（月火）
でも すぐやめました
なぜでしょう？
But we stopped right away, I wonder why?
（火憐）
そういや
１日で やめてたな
Yeah, it lasted only a day, why was that?
なんでなの？
Because of your messy bed hair, you couldn't even get a decent ponytail.
We can only request
the help of a god now!
（月火）
寄せていったものの
火憐ちゃんの
ナチュラル寝癖を
全く
再現できなかったから
"Mankind cannot win against nature", was it?
人間 自然には勝てない
ということですよ
That's not what I meant, apologize to me!
（火憐）
意味が違うし 私に謝れ
Next Time
Hitagi End Part 2
（２人）
次回「恋物語 第２話
ひたぎエンド 其ノ貳(そのに)」
Next time! Koimonogatari Episode 2!
Hitagi End, Part 2.
It's Nadeko-chan!
It's her!
（火憐）
副音声には
登場するらしいぜ
I hear we will be in the commentaries though.
（月火）
また副音声送りか
Sent off to commentaries again...?